<?xml version="1.0" encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
        "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry id="time.conf">

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>time.conf</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="sectdesc">Linux-PAM Manual</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>time.conf</refname>
    <refpurpose>configuration file for the pam_time module</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1 id='time.conf-description'>
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>

    <para>
      The pam_time PAM module does not authenticate the user, but instead
      it restricts access to a system and or specific applications at
      various times of the day and on specific days or over various
      terminal lines. This module can be configured to deny access to
      (individual) users based on their name, the time of day, the day of
      week, the service they are applying for and their terminal from which
      they are making their request.
    </para>
    <para>
      For this module to function correctly there must be a correctly
      formatted <filename>/etc/security/time.conf</filename> file present.
      White spaces are ignored and lines maybe extended with '\' (escaped
      newlines). Text following a '#' is ignored to the end of the line.
   </para>

    <para>
      The syntax of the lines is as follows:
    </para>

    <para>
      <replaceable>services</replaceable>;<replaceable>ttys</replaceable>;<replaceable>users</replaceable>;<replaceable>times</replaceable>
    </para>
    <para>
      In words, each rule occupies a line, terminated with a newline
      or the beginning of a comment; a '<emphasis remap='B'>#</emphasis>'.
      It contains four fields separated with semicolons,
      '<emphasis remap='B'>;</emphasis>'.
    </para>

    <para>
      The first field, the <replaceable>services</replaceable> field,
      is a logic list of PAM service names that the rule applies to.
    </para>

    <para>
      The second field, the <replaceable>tty</replaceable>
      field, is a logic list of terminal names that this rule applies to.
    </para>

    <para>
      The third field, the <replaceable>users</replaceable>
      field, is a logic list of users or a netgroup of users to whom this
      rule applies.
    </para>

    <para>
      For these items the simple wildcard '*' may be used only once.
      With netgroups no wildcards or logic operators are allowed.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <replaceable>times</replaceable> field is used to indicate the times
      at which this rule applies. The format here is a logic
      list of day/time-range entries. The days are specified by a sequence of
      two character entries, MoTuSa for example is Monday Tuesday and Saturday.
      Note that repeated days are unset MoMo = no day, and MoWk = all weekdays
      bar Monday. The two character combinations accepted are Mo Tu We Th Fr Sa
      Su Wk Wd Al, the last two being week-end days and all 7 days of the week
      respectively. As a final example, AlFr means all days except Friday.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each day/time-range can be prefixed with a '!' to indicate
      "anything but".
      The time-range part is two 24-hour times HHMM, separated by a hyphen,
      indicating the start and finish time (if the finish time is smaller
      than the start time it is deemed to apply on the following day).
    </para>

    <para>
      For a rule to be active, ALL of service+ttys+users must be satisfied
      by the applying process.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note, currently there is no daemon enforcing the end of a session.
      This needs to be remedied.
    </para>
    <para>
      Poorly formatted rules are logged as errors using
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>syslog</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="time.conf-examples">
    <title>EXAMPLES</title>
    <para>
      These are some example lines which might be specified in
      <filename>/etc/security/time.conf</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
      All users except for <emphasis>root</emphasis> are denied access
      to console-login at all times:
      <programlisting>
login ; tty* &amp; !ttyp* ; !root ; !Al0000-2400
      </programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
      Games (configured to use PAM) are only to be accessed out of
      working hours. This rule does not apply to the user
      <emphasis>waster</emphasis>:
      <programlisting>
games ; * ; !waster ; Wd0000-2400 | Wk1800-0800
      </programlisting>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="time.conf-see_also">
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <para>
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam_time</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam.d</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pam</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="time.conf-author">
    <title>AUTHOR</title>
    <para>
      pam_time was written by Andrew G. Morgan &lt;morgan@kernel.org&gt;.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
