<?xml version="1.0" encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      href="pam_namespace.8.xml" xpointer='xpointer(//refnamediv[@id = "pam_namespace-name"]/*)'/>
    </title>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[

pam_namespace module:
Setup a private namespace with polyinstantiated directories.

THEORY OF OPERATION:
The pam namespace module consults /etc/security/namespace.conf
configuration file and sets up a private namespace with polyinstantiated
directories for a session managed by PAM. A skeleton namespace.conf
installed by default provides example for polyinstantiating /tmp, /var/tmp
and users' home directory.

If an executable script /etc/security/namespace.init exists, it
is used to initialize the namespace every time a new instance directory
is setup. The script receives the polyinstantiated directory path
and the instance directory path as its arguments.

Each line in namespace.conf describes a limit for a user in the form:

<polydir>  <instance_prefix>  <method>  <list_of_uids>

Where:
<polydir> - is the absolute pathname of the directory to polyinstantiate
      Special entry $HOME is supported to designate user's home directory.
      This field cannot be blank.

<instance_prefix> - is the string prefix used to build the pathname for the
	instantiation of <polydir>. The directory security context, or
	optionally its md5sum string (32 hex characters), is appended to
        the prefix to generate the final instance directory path.
        This directory is created if it did not exist already, and is then
	bind mounted on the <polydir> to provide an instance of <polydir>
	based on the <method> column. The special string $HOME is replaced with
	the user's home directory, and $USER with the username.
	This field cannot be blank.

<method> - is the method used for polyinstantiation. It can take 3 different
	values; "user" for polyinstantiation based on user name, "context"
	for polyinstantiation based on process security context, and "both"
	for polyinstantiation based on both user name and security context.
	Methods "context" and "both" are only available with SELinux. This
	field cannot be blank.

<list_of_uids> - is a comma separated list of user names for whom the
	polyinstantiation is not performed. If left blank, polyinstantiation
	will be performed for all users.

EXAMPLE /etc/security/namespace.conf configuration file:
=======================================================
# Following three lines will polyinstantiate /tmp, /var/tmp and user's home
# directories. /tmp and /var/tmp will be polyinstantiated based on both
# security context as well as user name, whereas home directory will
# be polyinstantiated based on security context only. Polyinstantiation
# will not be performed for user root and adm for directories /tmp and
# /var/tmp, whereas home directories will be polyinstantiated for all
# users. The user name and/or context is appended to the instance prefix.
#
# Note that instance directories do not have to reside inside the
# polyinstantiated directory. In the examples below, instances of /tmp
# will be created in /tmp-inst directory, where as instances of /var/tmp
# and users home directories will reside within the directories that
# are being polyinstantiated.
#
# Instance parent directories must exist for the polyinstantiation
# mechanism to work. By default, they should be created with the mode
# of 000. pam_namespace module will enforce this mode unless it
# is explicitly called with an argument to ignore the mode of the
# instance parent. System administrators should use this argument with
# caution, as it will reduce security and isolation achieved by
# polyinstantiation.
#
/tmp     /tmp-inst/       	both      root,adm
/var/tmp /var/tmp/tmp-inst/   	both      root,adm
$HOME    $HOME/$USER.inst/inst- context

ARGUMENTS RECOGNIZED:
    debug
	Verbose logging by syslog

    unmnt_remnt
	For programs such as su and newrole, the login session has
	already setup a polyinstantiated namespace. For these programs,
	polyinstantiation is performed based on new user id or security
	context, however the command first needs to undo the
	polyinstantiation performed by login. This argument instructs
	the command to first undo previous polyinstantiation before
	proceeding with new polyinstantiation based on new id/context.

    unmnt_only
	For trusted programs that want to undo any existing bind mounts
	and process instance directories on their own, this argument
	allows them to unmount currently mounted instance directories.

    require_selinux
	If selinux is not enabled, return failure.

    gen_hash
	Instead of using the security context string for the instance
	name, generate and use its md5 hash.

    ignore_config_error
	If a line in the configuration file corresponding to a
	polyinstantiated directory contains format error, skip that
	line process the next line. Without this option, pam will return
	an error to the calling program resulting in termination
	of the session.

    ignore_instance_parent_mode
	Instance parent directories by default are expected to have
	the restrictive mode of 000. Using this option, an administrator
	can choose to ignore the mode of the instance parent.

MODULE SERVICES PROVIDED:
	session            open_session and close_session

USAGE:
	For the <service>s you need polyinstantiation (login for example)
	put the following line in /etc/pam.d/<service> as the last line for 
	session group:

	session  required  pam_namespace.so [arguments]

	This module also depends on pam_selinux.so setting the context.
]]>
    </programlisting>
  </section>
</article>

